( DISTANT HAMMERING )
( WOMAN SCREAMING )
MINISTER : " ... things I heard , as it were ,
" the voice of much people in heaven , saying ,
" Hallelujah .
" Salvation and glory and power is to our God .
" For true and just are his judgments ,
" who hath judged the great harlot which corrupted ...
" ... with her fornication ,
" and hath revenged the blood of his servants , at her hands .
" Come , gather yourselves together to the great supper of God .
" That you may eat the flesh of kings , and the flesh of tribunes ,
" and the flesh of mighty men , and the flesh of horses ,
" and of them that sit on them ,
" and the flesh of all freemen and bondmen ,
" and of little and of great .
" And I saw the beast , and the kings of the earth ,
" and their armies gathered together to make war with him
" that sat upon the horse ... "
Bring on some water !
" And the beast was taken , and with him the false prophet ,
" who wrought signs before him ,
" wherewith he seduced them who received the character of the beast ,
" and who adored his image .
" These two were cast alive into the pool of fire , burning with brimstone .
" And the rest were slain by the sword
" of him that sitteth upon the horse ...
" ... and all the birds were filled with their flesh . "
MALE NARRATOR : The year is 1645 .
England is in the grip of bloody civil war .
On the one side stand the Royalist party of King Charles ,
on the other , Cromwell 's Parliamentary party , the Roundheads .
The structure of law and order has collapsed .
Local magistrates indulge their individual whims ,
justice and injustice are dispensed
in more or less equal quantities
and without opposition ,
an atmosphere in which the unscrupulous revel
and the likes of Matthew Hopkins
take full advantage of the situation .
In a time where the superstitions of country folk
are still a powerful factor ,
Hopkins preys upon them ,
torturing and killing in a supposed drive
to eliminate witchcraft from the country
and doing so with the full blessingof what law there is .
However , his influence is confined largely
to the eastern sector of the country ,
East Anglia , which is held firmly in Cromwell 's grasp ,
but not so firmly that the Roundhead cavalry patrols
have everything their own way ,
for there still exists an ever-present threat
from the remnants of the Royalist armies ,
desperately foraging for food , horses and supplies .
Stop that , Richard .
What ?
What you 're thinking .
What am I thinking ?
Ungodly thoughts of your Sara , that 's my guess .
Thoughts of Sara , yes . Ungodly ?
Depends on how you look at it .
And you , a supporter of Cromwell ...
Hold your talking , you two .
Yes , sir . Of course , sir .
We 'll be stopping in a few minutes to give the horses a rest .
You can gabble all you want then .
15 minutes and we 'll be on our way again .
( SCREAMS )
Get down . Royalist snipers .
Probably only a few of them after food and horses .
We 'll flush the bastards out in no time .
Marshall , you stop behind to keep an eye on the nags .
The rest of you follow me and keep spread out .
SOLDIER : Captain , look ! There 's one !
CAPTAIN : I see him ! Follow !
( GUN FIRES )
( MAN SCREAMING )
CAPTAIN : Harcourt , this way .
Robert ?
Captain ?
Captain Gordon , is that you ?
We 're here , trooper Marshall .
It 's quite all right .
Getting a bit nervous , were you , lad ?
Aye , just a bit , sir .
Well , no need to worry . We got them all , I reckon ...
Not quite all . One of them got away , sir ,
though I put my sword in him first .
We 'd better move on out of this wood , then .
If he has got away , he could still be dangerous .
Swallow , bury Brace 's body as soon as you can .
Look out , sir !
( SCREAMS )
Thank you , trooper Marshall .
He was trying to kill you , sir .
I gather that , trooper .
It was a lucky shot , sir .
Yes .
Nevertheless , it could have ended my career for good .
Right , we move out .
Swallow , join us as soon as you 've finished your business here .
Harcourt , give him a hand to remove the bodies .
Yes , sir .
ROBERT : So , you granted young Richard here leave , did you , Captain ?
I did .
Aye , two days .
Then you 'll be away to see your girl , I suppose .
And how will she greet you ?
Just promoted cornet for killing King 's men .
She knows my reasons for fighting
and it 's only while the trouble lasts .
( ROBERT CHUCKLING ) What are you laughing at ?
Leave him be , Robert .
Can 't you see he 's in love ?
Aye , I 'm not ashamed of it , either .
A toast , lads , to the lovely women of Suffolk .
And may they keep their beds warm
for General Cromwell 's gallant men .
( SOLDIERS LAUGHING )
Come on , boy . Nearly home .
Well !
Master Marshall , welcome .
I trust you 're well , sir .
My body is as strong as ever ,
but the war continues ?
Aye , we still fight . And why ...
Well , my company 's recruiting .
I have two days ' leave .
Then you must eat with us this evening . I thank you , sir .
We still have good food for all you soldiers take it from us .
And ale . Come , we shall drink together .
After your experience ,
it is likely our village has grown
a little smaller for you , eh , Richard ?
Not so much smaller as lacking in promise , perhaps .
In Ipswich or Cambridge , a man might find better opportunities .
Richard , if you took Sara to wife ...
You mean , you 'd give us your blessing ?
You would take her away from here ?
You honor me , sir ,
but I only have a small farm that belonged to my father
and my soldier 's pay , which is ...
I am little concerned with your ill kept lands .
And still less for the silver you get for killing good Christians .
Well , forgive me . That was unjust .
But there is trouble coming to this village
and I want Sara far away before it arrives .
Surely Suffolk should be free from the King 's armies .
It 's not only the King 's armies which bring death this year .
A lack of order in the land encourages strange ideas .
You mean more rebellion ?
I 'm sorry , you have worries enough already .
But give me your word that you will soon take Sara away from here
and you shall ask her consent tonight .
You have my word on that , sir .
Good , Richard . Good .
That 's right , my dear .
Master Richard Marshall .
Farm boy into soldier .
Welcome back , Master Marshall .
I 'm glad to be back , Mistress Sara .
By the way , Sara , I expect the meal at the usual time .
( CHUCKLING ) Yes , Uncle .
Your uncle has agreed to our marriage .
Richard .
( RICHARD LAUGHING )
Oh , the army has taught you rough manners .
Sara , why is he frightened ?
There have been threats to us since you were last here .
Threats ? Why ?
We 've been called papists and idolaters ,
and filth chalked up on the walls .
They say we 're King 's creatures
and should be pilloried and worse .
Who says these things ?
We 've become outcasts in our own village .
Rest easy .
Now , no one shall harm you .
I put my oath to that .
Have you arranged a day for the wedding , Richard ?
No , sir .
Much depends on how the armies move .
Remember , it must be soon .
But how certain are your fears of this danger ?
Perhaps just an old man 's bad dream ,
and being an old man , I must early to my bed .
Good night , my dear .
Good night , Uncle .
Oh , and Sara , remember to seethe doors are well bolted .
Yes , Uncle .
And Richard , don 't keep Mistress Sara up too late .
Country women need full eight hours in their beds
if they 're to be proper wives and mothers .
Goodnight , Cornet .
Goodnight , sir .
And will you make a proper wife and mother , Sara ?
I still have much to learn , Richard .
I 'll teach you .
Now , didn 't your uncle just say you must early to bed ?
He did .
And isn 't he a wise man ? He is .
Right .
How much further , Matthew ?
You will not call me Matthew .
I 'm not one of your drinking cronies ,
carousing and wenching in the taverns .
Aye , you 're not that , sir .
Remember , John Stearne , you ride with me
only because you help me in my work .
Oh , you call it work ?
It 's the Lord 's work , a noble thing ...
And a profitable one .
The Good Lord paying in silver for every hanging .
That is blasphemy , Stearne . Hold your tongue .
I 'm merely an honest man who helps you get your confessions .
The law has prescribed due methods of interrogation .
And I have been blessed with the skills to carry them out .
Oh , stop your gabbling . We have work to do in Brandeston .
Who is it this time ?
- The message tells of a priest . - A priest ?
One who gives worship to Satan and calls him Lord .
Oh , with the priest himself a witch ,
there 'll be others corrupted , too , I 'm thinking .
You enjoy torture , don 't you , Stearne ?
And you , sir ?
Goodbye , sir .
LOWES : God be with you , Richard .
Goodbye , Richard . Goodbye , Sara .
I 'll see you again soon .
( BELL CHIMING )
Given up ale for star-gazing , Tom Salter ?
Not star-gazing , Master Marshall . Waiting .
What for ?
Matthew Hopkins , a lawyer .
Must be important , that you wait after dark .
It is , that .
Aye .
Well , if I see a lawyer on the road , I 'll tell him you 're here .
How far is it to Brandeston , friend ?
- About three miles . - Thank you .
- Are you the lawyer ? - Aye .
- Name of Hopkins ? - Aye , Matthew Hopkins .
And this is my assistant , John Stearne .
Why do you want to know , soldier ?
There 's some men from the village back there , waiting for you .
Aye , they sent for us .
What would a lawyer want in Brandeston ?
A man who may not be what he seems to be . Come Stearne .
- John Lowes is his name . - An evil man .
- A papist . - Yeah , burning candles and all .
That is no proof of witchcraft in itself .
Dressed himself in devil 's garments , he did .
- And made unholy signs . - Yeah , he did . I saw him .
I will find out the truth for you .
Have no fear , friends .
( KNOCKING ON DOOR )
Yes ?
John Lowes ?
So , it has come to this .
You accuse me , a priest , of working with the Devil .
We can only judge by the evidence .
And there 's a lot of that , old man .
I reject your accusations totally .
He 's going to give us trouble .
A simple confession , priest , that 's all we ask .
Help us .
We 've got a lot of work to do in Brandeston .
Leave my house , the pair of you .
I told you he was going to be difficult .
I reject your foul suggestions ! Leave here at once !
All you reject is the true God !
Take him , Stearne .
Look for the Devil 's marks upon him .
Right . Help us , you two .
( MUMBLING IN LATIN )
Look , he still prays to Satan .
Get on with your task .
If the Devil made you a priest ,
he 's going to have hidden his mark with a lot of care .
( SCREAMING )
To what purpose is this ?
When the Devil buys a soul ,
he marks the person 's flesh , so we will know him .
If such a mark is pricked , no blood will flow , nor pain be felt .
( SCREAMING )
Mistress Sara ? Mistress Sara ?
They 've come for him .
( BOTH CHATTERING )
Seems Satan has hidden his mark well , Matthew .
Set him to running .
Quick , then , you two , around the table .
And keep him moving .
You would be his niece .
Your name , child ?
Sara .
I am Matthew Hopkins , Witchfinder .
Being his niece , you , too , may be corrupted by Satan .
No , not his niece .
A foundling ,
taken in by him and his housekeeper .
- Are you telling me the truth , child ? - Yes , yes , of course .
When she died , I became his servant .
And you 've remained innocent all of these years ?
Yes , sir , entirely .
I trust you know the old man ?
Better than anyone .
In private talk , we may shed some light on his innocence .
Private ?
Yes , away from the distraction of the crowd .
Perhaps in the quiet of your room tonight ,
you might be able to help me prove him guiltless .
Would you release him now ?
You might be convinced tonight that this is all needless .
And you will make every effort to present the facts to me ?
You may come to my room tonight , sir .
At what hour ?
At 8 : 00 , if you 'll release him now .
All right . He can sleep in the jail , and we 'll be rid of him .
SALTER : Come on ! Get up , you papist bastard !
Has he confessed yet ?
Not a word .
Well , then stop this .
But he hasn 't confessed .
Take him to the jail . We 'll continue the interrogation tomorrow .
LOWES : Jail ...
You heard what he said .
Quiet down , you animal .
( WOMAN GIGGLING )
You know what , Marston ? There were these couple of right filthy girls ,
filthy they were !
Horrible to behold , horrible !
- Witches ? - Yes , both of them .
We hanged them , Matthew and me .
Matthew . You know Matthew , he 's my partner .
Did it take you long to get a confession out of them , John ?
Well , a couple of days with one of them , the other one ...
Do you want more ale , sir ?
SALTER : Go on , then ? Come on . What about the other one ? Tell us about her .
STEARNE : Oh , yeah , the other one .
Now , she was a real strange one , she was .
Loved us for it , like she wanted to get strung up .
Reckon that was the only bit of excitement she ever had .
Well , go on , then , Mr. Stearne .
Go on .
( GIRL SCREAMING )
HOPKINS : Sara , I 've come to question you .
You came here for a purpose , sir .
I came here to get your evidence about the priest .
He 's been kind to me .
Perhaps he had a motive .
Men sometimes have strange motives for the things they do .
I know .
My motive in coming here was to find the truth .
How about the priest , Master Hopkins ?
We 'll have done with him in a day or two .
Have no fear , child .
- He 's been good to mein his way . - He is an idolater .
He must confess and die . Stearne will see to that .
Oh , no , please ! Don 't let him be harmed , please !
You seek to protect a witch from rightful justice ?
Oh , no , not that , but couldn 't he be kept in a cell ?
He could do no harm from a prison cell . Oh , please !
But justice must be done , my dear .
Grant me this .
Please , Matthew .
HOPKINS : Past noon , you unkempt lout . Get up !
Get away !
( WOMAN WHIMPERING )
I need air .
( STEARNE RETCHING )
Where 's the priest ?
Where you put him , in the jail .
We 'll get him out and start questioning him , then , eh ?
- No . - What ?
He stays where he is .
But we have no confession at all .
I said we 'll leave him in the cell .
All right , then . All right .
What about the women ?
When are we going to start interrogating them ?
I hear tell they 've a good few witches around this place .
When you 're in fit condition .
I 'm fighting-fit as it is .
Oh , and where were you last night , Matthew ?
I hear tell you 've been a-wandering .
You hear tell too much , man .
( WOMAN CRYING )
You , there , old man .
Master Hopkins , the Witchfinder ,
he says you 're to be kept here , interrogated no further .
Where are you off to , John ?
I 'm going for a walk .
By myself .
( DOG BARKING )
( WOMAN SCREAMING )
STEARNE : Tell me ! Tell me ! Tell me !
Tell me that ! Come on ! Tell me !
Confess , witch !
Tell us your foul iniquities !
No !
Your familiars , woman . Confess !
( STEARNE LAUGHING )
Stop . For God 's sake , stop .
Quiet , old man , and be thankful you 're not getting the same .
( STEARNE YELLING AT WOMAN )
( WOMAN SCREAMING )
How many of them ? A dog ? A ferret ?
Come on , tell them !
John . The Witchfinder , he 's coming .
( WOMAN SCREAMING )
I trust you are using the prescribed methods , Stearne ?
Naturally .
Has she confessed ?
Well , give me time . She 's only been here an hour .
Continue with the interrogation .
I shall be gone for a while .
You 're always going off somewhere , sir , aren 't you ?
What do you mean ?
Nothing .
I 've been called over the hill to the next village .
I shall be back by tomorrow .
You will remain in charge here .
Carry on your work while you 're away , aye , sir ?
Indeed .
And the priest ?
I said to leave him be .
( WOMAN CRYING )
( SLAPPING )
( WOMAN SCREAMING )
What do you want ?
You .
Where 's Master Hopkins ?
Gone .
Gone ?
Where ?
Just gone .
He 's left me in charge .
( SCREAMING ) No ! No !
No !
And don 't think I don 't know why the old priest is being spared , eh ?
( STEARNE GRUNTING )
( SARA SCREAMING )
( DOG BARKING )
Stearne , the priest .
I 've changed my mind .
STEARNE : Confess !
Confess .
He confessed . You heard him .
I 've heard nothing yet , Master Hopkins .
Refresh Master Salter 's memory , Stearne .
You heard him .
You did , too .
Yes , Master Hopkins .
Witnesses .
( MOANING )
SALTER : Get up , you blasted witch ! Get up !
Come on !
( SOBBING )
( MAN YELLING )
( PEOPLE YELLING AND SCREAMING )
You are , all of you , confessed idolaters .
However , these proceedings
shall be carried out through due process of law .
What law demands , we shall satisfy .
You will each be tied in a prescribed fashion ,
and cast into the moat .
Should you then sink , we will know
that your confessions are false .
If on the other hand you are seen to swim or float ,
then your confessions of witchcraft are proven beyond a doubt
in the sight of God .
And you will be withdrawn from the water
and hanged by the neck until you are dead .
You can 't hang me . The law forbids it !
I 'm with child .
And who would want to make you pregnant , witch ?
( CROWD LAUGHING )
Quiet . Stearne , go on with your task .
( WOMAN CRYING )
WOMAN : Oh , God , help me !
( WOMAN SCREAMING )
WOMAN : No !
No !
LOWE : Help me ...
Hey , look ! One of them is gone already .
They swim .
The mark of Satan is upon them .
STEARNE : Give us a hand here ! Come on !
They must hang .
She was innocent .
God forgive you , Matthew Hopkins .
Jailer ,
take them to the tree .
The money from the magistrate , nine guineas in silver .
Good . Now we can leave .
- Good morning , soldier . - Good morning .
What 'll you be after in the way of horses , then , aye ?
A dozen or so for General Cromwell 's armies up north .
Well , lost a few , have you ?
Aye , at Cheriton Wood .
That 's a pretty sorry looking bunch of old nags
you got in there , friend .
The best we could find .
Then they 'll have to do .
A dozen you say , eh ?
Aye .
We 'll be back in Suffolk soon
where , thank God , they still breed strong horses .
Oh , I doubt you 'll find much better there .
I 'm just back from those parts .
The mounts up there are much like these .
Have you been through Brandeston at all , man ?
Brandeston ? Aye .
And a fine commotion they 're stirring up there .
What , over you taking their horses ?
No , nothing like that . A mass hanging .
- Who ? - Witches , I heard .
Two women and a priest .
Where was the priest from , man ?
Brandeston , I suppose .
A brave old boy for all his white hairs .
Was he a friend of yours ?
Two troopers , Gifford and Harcourt , will be here directly .
Have them take these horses here back to the regiment
and report that I 'm delayed .
I 'll join them further north . Do you understand ?
Yes , but where will you be going to ?
Anything else ?
( URGING HORSE )
Sara !
Sara ?
Sara .
Sara !
They took him and killed him . They said he was an idolater .
I know , I heard .
Sara ...
One of them , the Witchfinder ,
he ...
He ...
I didn 't want to ...
I thought I could save him .
I thought they 'd have pity .
We kneel before thee , oh , Lord , in humility
to ask for a blessing on our union .
We ask for forgiveness of our sins
and strength to lead righteous lives as man and wife .
We pray also for the soul of thy servant , John Lowes .
May he know eternal peace .
And it is in thy sight , oh , Lord , that I hereby swear
I shall not rest from the pursuit of his murderers
till they stand before thee , ready to answer to thee for their sins .
Take this money and whatever you need from the rectory and go to Lavenham .
- You 'll be safer there . - I will , Richard .
Find lodgings and stay there .
I 'll come to you .
I love you very much .
Oh , Richard !
( SOOTHING HORSE )
( SHEEP BLEATING )
Shepherd , I seek two men . Witchfinders , they call themselves .
They were said to be headed this way .
- Matthew Hopkins and his assistant ? - Aye .
I 've heard they 're in Hoxne ,
about four miles yonder , but I can 't be sure .
Thank you , Shepherd .
SHEPHERD : Get out !
( URGING HORSE )
Oh , come on , Johnny , give us a kiss .
Oh , get away from me .
Stop it , you dirty rascal !
Stop it !
STEARNE : Here , I 'll bet you two pennies .
Ale , soldier ?
Aye , to wash the dust from my throat .
- Another one for you ? - Aye , get a move on with it .
She 's got a powerful thirst still .
Landlord , I 'm looking for a man called Hopkins .
I heard he was coming this way .
Matthew Hopkins ?
Would you know where he is , friend ?
Aye , he 's gone to Cambridge today .
But you got an accusation to make ,
I 'll get your confession for you .
I do the pricking , you know , not Matthew .
I 'm your man , friend .
John Stearne , they call me .
( SCREAMING )
I 'm husband to Sara Lowes .
( WOMAN SCREAMING )
( BOTH GRUNTING )
- You all right , friend ? - Yeah .
- You better get out of here . - Yeah , I 'm going , don 't worry .
As for you , soldier , you are coming down to see the magistrate .
Am I ? Not with you .
( URGING HORSE )
Quick , Matthew !
For God 's sake , Stearne , what have you done ? Who was that ?
- Richard Marshall . - Who ?
He 's married to the girl , Sara .
How did he find you ?
He was looking for you .
He found out about Brandeston .
We 're going to have to separate .
I won 't run from him .
We have work to do down south in Lavenham .
Not me . He 's after our blood .
Seems to me he 's already had some of yours .
Well , he 's not going to have any more , you understand ?
You 're forgetting our powers .
He could be a witch .
He 's a man who 's out to kill both of us .
Then it appears to me that we should take steps to see to his death first .
Come . We travel to Lavenham .
I full well understand your feelings , Cornet ,
but you 're an officer of the army , a soldier ,
and desertion is punishable by death .
However , in this case , there are two factors
which will stay me from subjecting you to a full court-martial .
One , we are grouped here at Naseby
in preparation for a major assault on the Royalist armies .
We need every man we can get .
And you 're a pretty good soldier , most of the time .
Thank you , sir .
Secondly , I would sleep ill if I had to send to the gallows
a man who had saved my life .
But , Cornet , remember this .
If you should leave your command again ,
I will have no alternative but to throw the whole weight of military law against you .
Understand ?
Yes , sir .
Dismissed , Cornet .
And may God help you in your search , Cornet Marshall .
Robert , hello .
- Richard , you 're back . - Aye .
What happened with the Captain ?
Nothing .
I heard about Brandeston , Richard .
Hopkins and Stearne .
I 'll find them somewhere .
But what can you do ?
What proof have you that they committed any crime ?
I 've got Sara 's word on it .
Is that enough for the magistrates ?
There 'll be no magistrates involved .
What do you mean ?
We 'll talk more later , Richard .
We must be on our way .
We 're after horses for this skirmish that 's coming up .
All right .
Hup . Come on . Hup .
Parliament men , comrades of friend Marshall .
There 's some good ones coming now , look .
Hey !
Let 's make a run for it , shall we , while we can .
- Be calm - Yeah , but if they find out who we are ,
- they 'll ... - They won 't . Come on .
That 's a fine horse you 've got there , friend .
ROBERT : The army needs mounts of such caliber .
I am not selling .
But you will get your money when the war 's over .
You don 't appear to understand . I am not selling .
Oh , but you are selling , friend .
And we 'll take that one , there , too .
So you filthy soldier scan butcher my mare ?
Sergeant , he thinks we 're filthy soldiers . Do you hear ?
Aye , I heard .
You can 't go saying things like that , friend .
What he needs is a little army discipline .
I hear you need more pikemen in your platoon , Sergeant .
You 'll pay for this !
( HORSE WHINNYING )
Good horse you had , there . Cost a pretty penny , I reckon .
We robbed the canteen mint .
A right jester , he is .
Yeah , well , a day 's fighting in Cromwell 's army
will soon cure your wit , my lad .
I am not doing any fighting ,
neither for the King or your precious Cromwell , either .
You mark that well , soldier .
Yeah , you coward .
Just like your friend .
- Matthew Hopkins is no friend of mine . - Hopkins ?
The fancy boy who just made a fool of your cavalry , comrade .
- You rode with him . - I had reasons .
- He pays you ? - We were partners .
- In what business ? - Extermination .
- Eh ? - And what does that mean ?
( SCREAMS )
( GUN FIRES )
( PANTING )
( SCREAMS )
( STEARNE SCREAMING )
Now ,
Matthew Hopkins , sir .
Adequate , very adequate .
We did our best , sir .
Lavenham has served me well , Master Webb .
Now I must find out how I can serve you .
They 're all women , sir .
Strange , isn 't it , how much iniquity
the Lord vested in the female ?
Pardon , sir ?
Who makes the accusations ?
Myself , sir . I 'm representing the town .
- How many ? - Three , sir .
And what age ?
Well , two are young , sir , Elizabeth Clark and Mary Reynolds .
The other 's worn and old .
Fetch the young pair here to me .
What of the other hag ?
Well , the old ones are more sensible .
It 's the young ones who are stubborn .
They require time .
Oh , I see .
- Sir ? - Yes , man ?
Your assistant , sir .
We were told he , too , would be coming to Lavenham .
He 's engaged elsewhere .
He 's fighting for the Parliamentary cause .
Oh . He will be joining you here , sir ?
I really can 't say .
You can manage without him ?
Of course .
- I apologize ... - No .
Not only can I manage without him ,
but I intend to instigate a new method of execution ,
and you , Master Webb , you shall aid mein carrying it out .
What 's that , sir ?
You 'll see .
It 's a fitting end for the foul ungodliness in womankind .
Yes , sir .
Now , fetch that young pair here .
Sir .
An excellent meal , gentlemen .
There is little I find so satisfying
as good food after a well-earned victory .
- Wouldn 't you agree ? - Entirely , General .
The conflict at Naseby , sir , will go down as a triumph of your strategy .
Perhaps .
I would rather that it went down
as a triumph for the forces of true godliness .
Nevertheless , your name will symbolize the victory , sir .
Whether I like it or not , eh , Captain ?
That cornet you so highly recommended to me , is he to join us ?
He 's coming now , General Cromwell .
Good .
Amongst the most pleasurable aspects of victory , gentlemen ,
is the opportunity it affords to reward valor .
It ranks almost with good food .
Cornet Marshall , sir .
Mmm . All right . Rest , Cornet .
Your captain has told me about you .
He says you 're a good soldier .
Thank you , sir .
He recommends that I promote you to captain .
I thank you , sir .
I have a special mission for you , Captain .
Take three men and ride back into East Anglia .
The King has escaped us
and is rumored to be making for the Norfolk coast .
If that is the case , find and apprehend him
before he can escape to the continent .
It 's an honor , sir .
Pick your men . Start at once .
If you find the King , you will escort him then to Norwich .
If not , join us in the west .
Good luck , Captain .
Shall we rest up for the night , Richard ?
We 've got a job to do . We 'll go on till we 've done it .
Do you mean looking for the King ?
Or finding Hopkins and Stearne ?
Both .
Richard , you can 't go off and desert again .
I don 't plan to desert !
But supposing you do find out where they are ?
Then I shall take temporary leave again .
For God 's sake , Richard , I know how you feel ,
but to risk court-martial to kill Parliament 's own appointees ,
you 'll be hanged yourself .
Robert ! I 've taken an oath . I won 't break it !
It 's madness !
It 's justice !
It 's my justice .
HORSE SELLER : And what about one of them , sir ?
You won 't find better horseflesh in the whole of Suffolk .
So , how much you going to try to drag out of me if I take that one ?
He 's yours for a couple of guineas , sir .
A guinea .
A guinea and a half
for getting me out of bed at this hour of the morning .
One guinea .
And a quarter ?
I 'll quarter you .
You drive a hard bargain , sir .
Yeah .
And where would you be heading
that you need a horse in such a hurry ?
- To find my partner . - Your partner , eh ?
And what line of business might you be in ?
God 's business , witch-finding .
Witch-finding . Oh , that 's nice .
That 's very nice .
You wouldn 't make it a guinea and a quarter , would you ?
Do you know a man called Matthew Hopkins ?
You know where he is ?
I heard tell of such a man down south .
Lavenham , I believe .
What 's he doing in Lavenham ?
Extracting confessions , I don 't doubt .
You let me have that four-legged cripple now !
This happened three days ago . Why didn 't you report it to the militia then ?
How should we know it was the King himself ?
A stranger , obviously a townsman ,
tries to hire a boat to cross to France
and you suspect nothing ?
When the country 's torn by civil war ?
I didn 't know there was a war on
till you gentlemen told me so .
Oh , come on , Richard . We 'd better go back .
Aye , I suppose so . I want to pass through Lavenham and see how Sara is .
- Lavenham ? - Aye , how far is it from here ?
About two days ride , I reckon .
They got more excitement over there
than any of your city folk 's wars .
- What do you mean ? - They 're burning witches there , I hear .
Some such rigmarole .
They 're in Lavenham !
( RICHARD URGING HORSE )
Oy ! Richard !
( SCREAMING )
Elizabeth ! Elizabeth !
Oh , God !
All is ready , Master Hopkins ?
Aye .
Proceed with the executions , then .
Bring forth Elizabeth Clark .
( WOMAN SCREAMING ) Right . Siegel , fetch the rope .
MAN 1 : Get the rope .
MAN 2 : Oh , come on , you little bitch !
No ! Help !
No !
( SCREAMING )
Lower away .
Slowly , now . Keep her slow .
Elizabeth !
Master Hopkins , there are two more to be burned .
Yes , Magistrate . Master Webb , the others !
Here you are , 12 guineas in silver .
To be spent in the service of our Lord , Magistrate .
We must thank you for your good work , Master Witchfinder .
Thank you , Magistrate , for your aid .
Witchfinder !
Greetings , Stearne .
Is that all you 've got to say
after leaving me therewith Cromwell 's men ?
Well , I provided us both with the opportunity to escape .
Only you did and I was captured .
Fortunes of war , Stearne .
You know me well enough to know that I wouldn 't hesitate to fire and kill you .
Aye , you would that .
I hold all human life dearly , Stearne , especially my own .
Oh , come now .
You 've escaped and all is well .
Maybe .
I even saved your share of the pay
even though I did all of the work myself .
Now , are you going to be sensible or do I kill you ?
By the way , do you know what they call me now ?
What ?
Witchfinder General .
There are those who think
that I should be appointed such for all of England ,
appointed by Parliament .
Here ! Look .
Sara . She 's here .
Very nice , eh , Matthew ?
No , you fool .
Don 't you realize that if she 's here ,
that trooper must be around , too ?
But he 's away fighting .
Suppose he got leave after Naseby .
Where do you think he 'd go ? To see her , of course .
We better move along then , eh ? No .
That man , Marshall , is not going to give up .
He 's proved that to us already .
Then we have to get him before he gets us , right ?
We have the power to do it , legally .
Prove him a witch , huh ?
Exactly .
He 'd never confess , not that one .
On his own , no .
But if we had him and the girl ?
Yeah , she 's the niece of a man we executed for witchcraft .
And Marshall is her husband .
I owe that jumped-up plowboy a seeing-to .
Go out and ask around .
Find out if he 's been seen .
If not , we 'll tarry here a while until he does arrive .
( KNOCK ON DOOR )
- Who is it ? - RICHARD : Sara , open the door . It 's me .
Richard ?
They were here , Hopkins and Stearne .
I didn 't know what to do . I saw them in the street .
- I didn 't know if they saw me or not . - I know .
I know .
Well , I 'll be in the tavern with the others , then .
He 's here , Matthew ! Just arrived .
- Where 's he gone ? - To see the girl .
- Alone ? - Yeah . The three others are in the tavern .
Go and get us an extra man to help .
Where are we going to take them , Matthew ?
Up to the castle .
The magistrate here is very helpful .
That 's where you interrogated the others , is it ?
Yes .
Now , hurry to it , man .
What are you going to do ?
You say Hopkins arrived two days ago .
Yes , and then he was with the other one in the street today .
And they haven 't left yet ?
I 'm not sure . I 've been too scared to leave .
HOPKINS : Come on ! Open up in there !
( KNOCKING ON DOOR )
Drop that sword , soldier .
This man accuses you , Sara Lowes , and you , Richard Marshall ,
of consorting with the Devil .
- Is that not so , Master Webb ? - It is that , sir .
Will you describe your evidence to us ?
I observed the accused talking with their familiars
and making the signs of Satan , sir .
And what were these familiars to which you refer ?
Black cat and a stoat , sir .
You 're a very observing citizen , Master Webb .
Well , Sara , do you confess ?
And what do you have to say , soldier ?
I 'm going to kill you , Hopkins .
I don 't think you 'll find that easy .
The law is with me , remember ?
And what are you ? An accused witch .
They must be submitted to the test .
Take them , Stearne .
Hopkins !
( SCREAMING )
HOPKINS : A Royalist sympathizer , evidently .
But what are we going to do with him ?
Leave him . I 'll inform the magistrate later .
We have more important work to do .
Come on .
Get moving .
Orders from the magistrate . Suspected witches .
Yes , sir . Sorry , sir .
I heard them .
ROBERT : Where are they taking them ?
To the castle to test them .
Test them ?
They 're accused of witchcraft .
- Harcourt , you come with me . - Yes , sir .
Shall I look after him , sir ?
Yes , try and find him a physician .
I 've heard much of how Hopkins conducts his interrogations .
Come on , Harcourt .
( COUGHS )
All right , Stearne .
( SARA AND RICHARD SCREAMING )
( SARA WHIMPERING )
( SCREAMING )
SARA : No !
Well , Captain Marshall , do you now confess ?
Keep at it , Stearne . You 're doing God 's work .
( SARA SCREAMING )
Put her over here .
And you , Master Webb , help him .
Master Hopkins and his assistants , are they here , man ?
- That they are , sir . - Well , let us pass , then .
You 're here to help the Witchfinder ?
We 're here to find him , yes .
Have you a signed pass ?
Sara , I 'm going to place this iron on your back .
Should you faint or cry out ,
we can only take it that Satan has intervened to spare you your agony .
However , I could show mercy if ...
If Captain Marshall were to confess to witchcraft first .
But will you do it , sir ?
I shall kill you .
So , you have no proper authorization , then .
What do you mean ?
From the magistrate . Authorization .
Not here with us , no .
Well , we 'll go back and get one then .
All right . Then I 'll let you pass .
Master Webb , go and see what is the matter .
Yes , Master Hopkins .
What do we do , Matthew ?
We shall carry on with God 's work as before , man .
And fetch Captain Marshall over here .
He shall kneel before his wife and watch her suffer .
- But Matthew ... - Go do it , man !
( SCREAMS )
Oh , God !
You took him away from me .
You took him from me .
You took him from me !
( YELLING ) You took him from me !
( SOBBING )
May God have mercy on us all .
( SCREAMING HYSTERICALLY )